Guide to the Montana Conservation Districts Bureau Records 1940-1999
Montana Historical Society
Montana Conservation Districts Bureau Records
1940-1999
Montana Historical Society Archives
RS 337
Montana. Conservation Districts Bureau.
18.4 linear feet of shelf space
These records (1940-1999) of the Conservation Districts Bureau of the Montana Department of Natural Resources and Conservation consist of minutes. The collection is arranged alphabetically by conservation district.
In response to a preceived threat to the farm and grazing lands of Montana, the 1939 state Legislative Assembly created a State Soil Conservation Committee to "conserve soil resources and control and prevent soil erosion." The committee was composed of seven members, including the director of the state agricultural experiment station, the director of the state extension service, one members of the state grazing commission, one member of the water conservation board, and the commissioner of the state department of agriculture. Two additional members were to be farmers chosed by the governor. The primary duty of the Committee was to supervise and offer assistance to the soil conservation districts established around the state. Soil conservation district could be established by any ten occupiers of land within a given area where there was a need and interest in soil conservation. Conservation districts were considered a government office and were to study soil erosion, educate the public, and take active measures to correct erosion. In 1961 the name of the State Soil Conservation Committee and the name of the conservation districts were changed to reflect the addition of water conservation to their duties. The soil and water conservation districts were to monitor water conservation as well as soil erosion. The name was again changed in 1971, to the State Conservation Commission. Following the reorganization of state government in 1972, oversight of conservation districts was moved from a commission to the Department of Natural Resources and Conservation. The Conservation District Bureau currently oversees conservation districts and operates in the Conservation and Resource Development Division of the Department of Natural Resources and Conservation.
These records consist of minutes of conservation district meetings. They are arranged alphabetically by the name of the district.
The collection is arranged by series.
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information is available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Conservation of natural resources--Montana; Soil conservation districts--Montana
Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Minutes
  - Beaverhead Conservation District, 1952-1994 (Box-folder 1 / 1-5)
  - Bighorn Conservation District, 1944, 1951-1998 (Box-folder 1 / 6-14)
  - Bighorn Conservation District, 1944, 1951-1998 (Box-folder 1 / 6-14)
  - Big Sandy Conservation District, 1947-1992, 1996 (Box-folder 1 / 15-19)
  - Bitterroot Conservation District, 1943-1996 (Box-folder 2 / 1-13)
  - Blaine Conservation District, 1951-1957, 1959-1998 (Box-folder 2 / 14-19)
  - Broadwater Conservation District, 1949-1998 (Box-folder 3 / 1-8)
  - Carbon Conservation District, 1949-1950, 1954, 1957-1999 (Box-folder 3 / 9-16)
  - Carter Conservation District, 1944, 1948-1972 (Box-folder 3 / 17-19)
  - Carter Conservation District, 1973-1998 (Box-folder 4 / 1-4)
  - Cascade Conservation District, 1946, 1949-1998 (Box-folder 4 / 5-14)
  - Chouteau Conservation District, 1943-1982 (Box-folder 4 / 15-18)
  - Chouteau Conservation District, 1983-1998 (Box-folder 5 / 1-3)
  - Culbertson Conservation District, 1941-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 4-11)
  - Custer Conservation District, 1950, 1951, 1960, 1961-1998 (Box-folder 5 / 12-17)
  - Daniels Conservation District, 1947-1998 (Box-folder 6 / 1-5)
  - Dawson Conservation District, 1948, 1950, 1957-1998 (Box-folder 6 / 6-11)
  - Deer Lodge Conservation District, 1950-1998 (Box-folder 6 / 12-17)
  - East Sanders Conservation District, 1949-1980 (Box-folder 6 / 18-20)
  - East Sanders Conservation District, 1981-1996 (Box-folder 7 / 1-2)
  - Fergus Conservation District, 1950-1997 (Box-folder 7 / 3-6)
  - Flathead Conservation District, 1945-1947, 1950-1998 (Box-folder 7 / 7-14)
  - Gallatin Conservation District, 1950-1980, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 7 / 15-17)
  - Gallatin Conservation District, 1987-1998 (Box-folder 8 / 1-3)
  - Garfield Conservation District, 1949-1951, 1957-1998 (Box-folder 8 / 4-7)
  - Glacier Conservation District, 1949, 1951-1956, 1961-1972, 1974-1976, 1978-1998 (Box-folder 8 / 8-11)
  - Granite Conservation District, 1954-1978, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 8 / 12-13)
  - Green Mountain Conservation District, 1943, 1949-1955, 1958-1982 (Box-folder 8 / 13-17)
  - Green Mountain Conservation District, 1983-1998 (Box-folder 9 / 1-5)
  - Hill Conservation District, 1946-1998 (Box-folder 9 / 6-11)
  - Jefferson Valley Conservation District, 1948, 1950-1998 (Box-folder 9 / 12-16)
  - Judith Basin Conservation District, 1948-1984, 1987-1997 (Box-folder 10 / 1-5)
  - Lake Conservation District, 1946-1947, 1949-1950, 1952-1992 (Box-folder 10 / 6-8)
  - Lewis & Clark Conservation District, 1948-1998 (Box-folder 10 / 9-15)
  - Liberty Conservation District, 1950-1975 (Box-folder 10 / 16-17)
  - Liberty Conservation District, 1976-1998 (Box-folder 11 / 1-4)
  - Lincoln (Tobacco Valley) Conservation District, 1951-1996 (Box-folder 11 / 5-11)
  - Little Beaver Conservation District, 1948-1952, 1969-1984, 1988-1997 (Box-folder 11 / 12-15)
  - Lower Musselshell Conservation District, 1943-1944, 1950-1972, 1974-1977, 1979-1986, 1989, 1991, 1993- 1995 (Box-folder 11 / 16-17)
  - Madison Conservation District, 1947-1948, 1951-1976 (Box-folder 12 / 1-2)
  - McCone Conservation District (Contains 3 folders of un- processed election records), 1943-1945, 1949-1984, 1986, 1993- 1999 (Box-folder 12 / 3-12)
  - Meagher Conservation District, 1958-1964, 1966-1998 (Box-folder 12 / 13-15)
  - Mile High Conservation District, 1969-1974, 1976, 1978-1998 (Box-folder 12 / 16-18)
  - Mineral Conservation District, 1946, 1948-1952, 1956-1979, 1982-1985, 1989-1990, 1992 (Box-folder 12 / 19-20)
  - Missoula Conservation District, 1949-1998 (Box-folder 13 / 1-6)
  - North Powell Conservation District, 1950-1951, 1953-1998 (Box-folder 13 / 7-10)
  - Park Conservation District, 1950-1951, 1953, 1957-1998 (Box-folder 13 / 11-16)
  - Petroleum Conservation District, 1951-1955, 1960- 1998 (Box-folder 14 / 1-3)
  - Phillips Conservation District, 1950-1953, 1956-1998 (Box-folder 14 / 4-8)
  - Pondera Conservation District, 1949, 1953-1998 (Box-folder 14 / 9-14)
  - Powder River Conservation District, 1954, 1958-1968, 1970-1985 (Box-folder 14 / 15-16)
  - Prairie Conservation District, 1976-1985, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 14 / 17)
  - Richland Conservation District, 1940, 1943-1944, 1948- 1998 (Box-folder 15 / 1-7)
  - Roosevelt Conservation District (fsee also: Culbertson-Bainville Conservation District), 1941-1942, 1944-1945, 1962-1971, 1977-1984 (Box-folder 15 / 8-11)
  - Rosebud Conservation District, 1942, 1944, 1951-1999 (Box-folder 15 / 12-17)
  - Ruby Valley Conservation District, 1951-1998 (Box-folder 16 / 1-7)
  - Sheridan Conservation District, 1939-1998 (Box-folder 16 / 8-16)
  - Stillwater Conservation District, 1955-1974 (Box-folder 16 / 17-18)
  - Stillwater Conservation District, 1975-1992 (Box-folder 17 / 1-2)
  - Sweet Grass Conservation District, 1953-1996 (Box-folder 17 / 3-7)
  - Sun River Conservation District, 1948-1954, 1958-1960 (Box-folder 17 / 8)
  - Teton Conservation District, 1948-1997 (Box-folder 17 / 9-14)
  - Three Forks Conservation District, 1945, 1950-1959, 1961-1966, 1968 (Box-folder 17 / 15-16)
  - Treasure Conservation District, 1950-1965, 1968-1982 (Box-folder 17 / 17-18)
  - Treasure Conservation District, 1983-1984, 1986, 1989, 1993-1998 (Box-folder 18 / 1-2)
  - Toole Conservation District, 1949-1995, 1996 (Box-folder 18 / 3-8)
  - Upper Musselshell Conservation District, 1951-1952, 1954, 1957-1984, 1986, 1993-1994, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 18 / 9-11)
  - Nashua/Valley Conservation District, 1950-1984, 1986, 1993-1998 (Box-folder 18 / 12-15)
  - Wibaux Conservation District, 1951, 1954, 1957-1984, 1986 (Box-folder 18 / 16-18)
  - Yellowstone Conservation District, 1950-1954, 1959-1984, 1986, 1993-1999 (Box-folder 19 / 1-5)